Guide to the Cabié Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Cabié collection
0400-1799
MS 122
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
43
(103 boxes)
Manuscript copies of documents in the Bibliothèque Nationale, the Archives Nationales and other archival sources in France, almost all relating to religious questions in the Languedoc region. The copies, which were made at the turn of the century, are contained in 373 volumes. Two collections from the Bibliothèque Nationale make up the major portion of the collection: The Collection de Languedoc (48 v.).
Cabiʹe, Edmond, 1846-1909
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased in 1928.
Biographical / Historical
Scholar; Studied at the Polytechnique in 1865, but did not complete his work there. Returned to the Languedoc region and devoted his time toward editing texts, and studying prehistoric history and archaeology. A major work by Cabié was Guerres de religion dans le sud-est de la France, 1906.
Scope and Contents
The Cabié Collection consists of a number (380 vol.) of copies of manuscripts which were made at the turn of the century by E. Cabié and others. The copies are hand-written and usually clearly legible; the collection is in good state of repair; the paper is not brittle and the volumes are well bound.
The purpose of Cabié's work was to collect as much material as possible about the Languedoc (which he defines as the area west of the Rhône, south of the Tarn and north of the Pyrénées). Cabié thus went through the Bibliothèque Nationale and the Archives Nationales, selecting those manuscripts which pertained to his field and had them copied.
The Cabié Collection and the Bénédicitins Collection.
The Doat Collection. The Doat Collection consists of copies made by M. Doat, President of the Chambre des Comptes de Naverre, and others, under Colbert's orders. The purpose of this endeavor was to give Colbert an idea of the extent and nature of royal privileges in the Languedoc. The collection thus consists exclusively of copies of manuscripts which Doat made in the Languedocian archives; publics, municipal, and monastical. Doat's survey, according to Cabié, was exhaustive and the copies remarkably accurate.
These copies were filed by Doat as well as Cabié in two ways: 1) by subject of study: heretics (allegories, heresy), 28 volumes; Crusades, 4 volumes; French history, general and 2) by locality (and chronologically): Albi, 15 volumes; Rodez, 10 volumes; Foix, 30 volumes.
According to Cabié, the Doat Collection, as he copied it, is the richest collection available on the Languedoc. The material on Albi and the heresy is particularly extensive.
The Benedictins Collection was not copied in its entirety. Nonetheless, Cabié filled 40 volumes of his collection with this material. Benedictins refers to two Benedictine monks: Dom de Vic and Dom Vaissete, who lived during the XVIII century and who wrote the Histoire Générale du Languedoc. The Collection comprises their notes and materials: 1) notes: geographical notes refer to the XVIII th century and are filed by locality, 5 volumes and historical notes (1200-1600); also filed by locality, genealogical notes. 2) documents, 28 volumes of manuscripts, charters, letters. Filed chronologically (400?-1600). Senechaussé records for the Languedoc, filed by date (1272-1585).
The Boat and Benedictins Collections account for 220 out of 380 of Cabié's volumes. The remainder includes copies of choice of manuscripts found in the Bibliothèque Nationale. and the Archives Nationales. Cabié's arrangement of the copies is according to the Collection from which they were made:
1.) Fonds Latin (Biblioth. Nat.) 15 volumes concern early Languedoc history (7th-13th century). Emphasis is on religious matters.
2.) Fonds Francais (Biblioth. Nat.): 2 collections of 16th century correspondence, 5 volumes; 40 volumes of copies of manuscripts of the Trésor des Chartes (an XVIIIth century collection of copies and originals of manuscripts — a centralized general archive). Cabié selected the useful (i.e. Languedoc) materials and had them copied (1250-1500); and Serilly Collection (same structure as Doat.) Serilly was a colleague of Doat's), arranged chronogically.
3.) Baluze Collection. (Biblioth. Nat.) 3 volumes. Religious. (Languedoc)
4.) Moreau Collection. (Biblioth. Nat.) 2 vamps. Religious. (Biblioth. Nat.)
5.) Hozier Collection. 1 volums; list of nobles in Languedoc.
6.) Trésor des Chartes. (Archives Nationales.) Concerning the relationships of authority (royal privileges, relationships between local nobles.) 40 volumes, chronologically arranged (1250-1450).
7.) Monuments Historiques. (Archives Nationales.) 3 volumes. Sénéchauseé of Toulouse records, 14th century.
Arrangement
The materials are arranged in the following sections: Collection Doat (Bibliothèque Nationale), Collection du Languedoc (Bénédictins) (Bibliothèque nationale), Fonds Latin (Bibliothèque nationale), Fonds Français (Bibliothèque nationale), Collection Baluze (Bibliothèque nationale), Collection Moreau (Bibliothèque nationals), Hozier (Bibliothèque nationale), Trésor des Chartes (Archives nationales), and Monuments historiques (Archives nationales).
Collection Doat (Bibliothéque Nationale)
Collection du Languedoc (Bénédictins) (Bibliothéque nationale)
Fonds Latin (Bibliothéque nationale)
Fonds Français (Bibliothéque nationale)
Collection Baluze (Bibliothéque nationale)
Collection Moreau (Bibliothéque nationals)
Hozier/ (Bibliothéque nationale)
Trésor des Chartes (Archives nationales)
Monuments historiques (Archives nationales)
[Appendices]
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open for research.
Europe; France -- History; France -- Religion; Languedoc (France) -- History; Cabiʹe, Edmond, 1846-1909
- Collection Doat (Bibliothèque Nationale)
  Scope and Contents
  [Made at different archives in the South for Colbert, between 1665 and 1670, and sent to Paris by Jean de Doat, président de la Chambre des Comptes de Navarre. For a full description, see Bibliothèque Nationale, Collections manuscrites sur l'histoire des provinces de France: inventaire par Ph. Lauer.Tome I, Paris 1905, pp.xii-xiii, 156-192. (Xx81.B905. v.l). Partial but detailed accounts of contents are found in the " Cabinet historique", III, 2e partie (Ba3.19)
  IV, 2e partie, (vol.1l8: Cahors: Lot)
  VI, 2e partie, (vol.1l8: Comté d'Armagnac)
  VII, 2e partie (vol.1l8: Moissac)
  XI, 2e partie (vol.1l8: Millau)
  XIV, 2e partie (vol.1l8: Villefranche)
  XX, 2e partie (vol.1l8: Albigeois & Albret).
  Also see abbé Martin, "Table des volumes de la collection Doat qui concernent le Lot," ("Balletin de la Société des études littéraires du Lot", II, 1875, p.233). Briefer descriptions are in:-
  Deliole, "Catalogue des actes de Philip Auguste", pp.xxix, xlv, and in the "Bibliothèque de 1'Ecole des chartes", XXXII, 1871, pp.252–255]
  [Some documents in the collection have been published in:-
  " Histoire générale de Languedoc", new edition; Saige, "Les Juifs de Languedoc au Moyen âge", 1881; works by Edmond Cabié; etc., etc.]
  - Inventaires des copies.)
  - De la France en général; 811-1585 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Affaires écclesiastiques (Box 1, Folder 2-4)
  - Affaires religieuses: croisades, ordres, etc. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Supplément. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Hérétiques (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Hérétiques Supplément (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Hérétiques (Box 3, Folder 9-11)
  - Hérétiques (Box 4, Folder 12-14)
  - Hérétiques (Box 5, Folder 15-18)
  - Hérétiques (Box 6, Folder 19-21)
  - Hérétiques et Juifs. (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - Mariages de la noblesse. (Box 7, Folder 23)
  - Testaments (Box 7, Folder 24-25)
  - Testaments (Box 8, Folder 26)
  - Mariages of testaments. Supplément. (Box 8, Folder 27)
  - Mariages of testaments. 2e Supp. (Box 8, Folder 28)
  - Vicomté de Narbonne, 1035-1655 (Box 9, Folder 29)
  - Narbonne ville, 1166-1561. (Box 9, Folder 30)
  - Evêché de Narbonne, 816-1547 (Box 9, Folder 31)
  - Chapitra de S. Paul et des abbayes de Narbonne, 911-1616 (Box 9, Folder 32)
  - Narbonne. Supplément (Box 10, Folder 33)
  - Béziers: ville, couvents, évêché. (Box 10, Folder 34)
  - Béziers: Supplément (Box 10, Folder 35)
  - Carcassonne: ville et couvents, 1112-1642 (Box 11, Folder 36)
    General note
    missing
  - Carcassonne: évêché, 926-1607 (Box 11, Folder 37)
  - Abbaye de La Grasse, 806-1646 (Box 11, Folder 38)
  - Abbaye de Montolieu, 815-1565 (Box 11, Folder 38)
  - Abbayes de Villelongue, 1145-1428, de S. Hilaire da S. Tibéry, d'Alet, et des évêchés d'Agde, de Lodèves et de Montpellier, Nimes, Aigues-Mortes, S. Pons de Tomières, 1078-1600. (Box 11, Folder 39)
  - Carcassonne, diocèse de, +C. Supp. (Box 11, Folder 40)
  - Carcassonne, diocèse de, +C. Pamiers et Foix Supp. (Box 11, Folder 41)
  - Toulouse, ville et couvents, 854-1596 (Box 11, Folder 42)
  - Actes d'Alphonse de Poitiers, comte de Toulouse, 1229-1271. (Box 12, Folder 43)
  - Hommages, actes, reconnaissances aux rois, 1209-1303. (Box 12, Folder 44)
  - Abbaye de Grandselve, 1113-1514. (Box 12, Folder 45)
  - Abbaye de Grandselve, 1113-1514. (Box 13, Folder 46-47)
  - Abbaye de Grandselve, 1113-1514. (Box 14, Folder 48-49)
  - Lavaur, villa et chapitre, 810-1526 (Box 14, Folder 50)
  - Evêché at seigneuries de Mirepoix; monastère de S. Michel de Cuxa, xe siècle-1577 (Box 15, Folder 51)
  - Abbaye de Bolbonne, 962-1605 (Box 15, Folder 52)
  - Abbaye de Bolbonne, 962-1605 (Box 16, Folder 53-54)
  - Abbaye de Bolbonne, 962-1605 (Box 17, Folder 55)
  - Montauban, vile, 1144-1611. (Box 17, Folder 56-57)
  - Montauban, abbaye & collégiale, 1121-1600 (Box 18, Folder 58)
  - Montauban, abbaye (Box 18, Folder 59)
  - Montauban: abbaye de Bellepercha, 1164-1557 (Box 18, Folder 60)
  - Castelsarrasin, 1235-1598 (Box 18, Folder 61)
  - Pamiers; ville, 1232-1546 (Box 19, Folder 62)
  - Pamiers; abbaye & évêché (Box 19, Folder 63)
  - Pamiers>: évêché Tarasoon, etc. (Box 19, Folder 64)
  - Foix, villa, et abbaye de S. Volusien, 1144-1594. (Box 19, Folder 65)
  - Abbayes du Mas d'Azil, etc., + ville de Lectoure, 1009-1574. (Box 20, Folder 66)
  - Prieuré de Prouille, 1269-1388; abbaye a Lézat, 726-1549 (Box 20, Folder 67)
  - abbaye de Lézat (Box 20, Folder 68)
  - abbaye de Lézat (Box 20, Folder 69-70)
  - abbaye de Lézat (Box 21, Folder 71)
  - Prouille + Lésat. Supp. (Box 21, Folder 72)
  - Albi, 924-1618 (Box 21, Folder 73-74)
  - Albi, 924-1618 Supp. (Box 22, Folder 75)
  - Albi, 924-1618 (Box 22, Folder 76-79)
  - Albi, 924-1618 (Box 23, Folder 80-83)
  - Albi, 924-1618 1er supp. (Box 24, Folder 84)
  - Albi, 924-1618 2e supp. (Box 24, Folder 85)
  - Albi, 924-1618 (Box 24, Folder 86)
  - Albi, 924-1618 Supp. (Box 24, Folder 87)
  - Albi abbaye de Candelles, 1153-1586 (Box 25, Folder 88-89)
  - Gaillac, 972-1527 (Box 25, Folder 90)
  - Divers établissements des diocèses d'Albi, de Castres, de Mende, de Bordeaux, d'Agen, de Saintes, de Bourges, de Rodez, de Clermont, et du Puy; + 1'occupation anglaise en Guyenne. IX e s.-1559. (Box 25, Folder 90)
  - Albi, +c. Supp. (Box 25, Folder 91)
  - Cahors; ville et évêché, 1166-1621. (Box 26, Folder 92)
  - Cahors; ville et évêché Supp. (Box 26, Folder 93)
  - Cahors: collèges, universityé, abbayes, hôpital, etc., 1100-1661. (Box 26, Folder 94)
  - Cahors:>abb. de Marcillac (Box 26, Folder 95)
  - Cahors:monistères VIII e s.-1593 (Box 26, Folder 96)
  - Cahors:monistères VIII e s.-1593 Supp.] (Box 27, Folder 97)
  - Moissac: ville, 1197-1519 (Box 27, Folder 98)
  - Moissac: abbaye, 672-1618, etc. (Box 27, Folder 99-100)
  - Moissac: abbaye, 672-1618, etc. (Box 28, Folder 101-102)
  - Moissac: abbaye, 672-1618, etc. Supp. (Box 28, Folder 103)
  - Rodex, 814-1589 (Box 28, Folder 104)
  - Rodex dommorie, à 1635 Collégiale de Beaumont, 1140-1607, etc. (Box 29, Folder 105)
  - Rodex. Supp. (Box 29, Folder 106)
  - Rodex. abb. de Bonne-Combe, 1168-1531 (Box 29, Folder 107)
  - Rodex. abb. de Bonne-Combe, supp. (Box 30, Folder 108)
  - Rodex. abb. da Bonneval, 1161-1630, et de Coulommiersen-Brie, 371-1571 (Box 30, Folder 109)
  - Rodex. villes de Millan, 1070-1587, et de Najac et 5. Antonin, 1085-1601. (Box 30, Folder 110)
  - Villefranche-de-Rouergue, 1256-1588. (Box 30, Folder 111)
  - Évêché de Vabres, 864-1860; ville de s. Affrique, abbs de Monengues + de Nant, 1135-1453 (Box 31, Folder 112)
  - Vabres: abb. de Salvanès, 1096-1539. (Box 31, Folder 113)
  - Vabres: abb. de Salvanès, 1096-1539. Supp. (Box 31, Folder 114)
  - Vabres: abb. de Salvanès 2e. Supp. (Box 31, Folder 114a)
  - Province d'Auch, 1088-1546 (Box 31, Folder 115)
  - Ordonnances, bulles, actes, et hommages, du Languedoc, 1068-1569 (Box 31, Folder 116)
  - Ordonnances, bulles, actes, et hommages, du Languedoc, 1068-1569. Supp. (Box 32, Folder 117)
  - Ordonnances, bulles, actes, et hommages, du Languedoc, 1068-1569. (Box 32, Folder 118)
  - Ordonnances, bulles, actes, et hommages, du Languedoc, 1068-1569. Supp. (Box 32, Folder 119-120)
  - Bretagne, Lorraine, Urgel, Vic, Castile, Aragon, Maforque, 969-1527 (Box 33, Folder 121)
  - Foix, chronique et inventaire du comté (Box 33, Folder 122)
  - Vicomtés de Béziers; comtés de et, 960-1169 (Box 33, Folder 123)
  - Vic. du Béziers, 1170-1246 (Box 33, Folder 124)
  - Supp. (Box 33, Folder 125)
  - 2e Supp. (Box 34, Folder 126)
  - Comtés de Foix et Armagnac, et Rodez, 1247-1278. (Box 34, Folder 127)
  - Comtés de Foix et Armagnac, et Rodez Supp. (Box 34, Folder 128)
  - Comtés de Foix et Armagnac, et Rodez, 1279-1303. (Box 34, Folder 129)
  - Comtés de Foix et Armagnac, et Rodez Supp. (Box 35, Folder 130)
  - Comtés de Foix et Armagnac, et Rodez, 1304-1314. (Box 35, Folder 131)
  - Comtés de Foix et Armagnac, et Rodez Supp. (Box 35, Folder 132)
  - Comtés de Foix et Armagnac, et Rodez, 1315-1329. (Box 35, Folder 133)
  - Comtés de Foix et Armagnac, et Rodez Supp. (Box 36, Folder 134)
  - Comtés de Foix et Armagnac, et Rodez, 1330-1388. (Box 36, Folder 135)
  - Comtés de Foix et Armagnac, et Rodez Supp. (Box 36, Folder 136)
  - Comtés de Foix et Armagnac, et Rodez, 1343-1361 (Box 37, Folder 137)
  - Comtés de Foix et Armagnac, et Rodez Supp. (Box 37, Folder 138)
  - Comtés de Foix et Armagnac, et Rodez, 1343-1361. Supp. (Box 37, Folder 139)
  - Comtés de Foix et Armagnac, et Rodez, Circa1360-1380. (Box 37, Folder 140)
  - Comtés de Foix et Armagnac, et Rodez Supp. (Box 37, Folder 141)
  - Comtés de Foix et Armagnac, et Rodez, 1362-1372. (Box 38, Folder 142)
  - Comtés de Foix et Armagnac, et Rodez Supp. (Box 38, Folder 143)
  - Comtés de Foix et Armagnac, et Rodez, 1374-1379. (Box 38, Folder 144)
  - Comtés de Foix et Armagnac, et Rodez Supp. (Box 38, Folder 145)
  - Comtés de Foix et Armagnac, et Rodez, 1380-1391 (Box 39, Folder 146)
  - Comtés de Foix et Armagnac, et Rodez Supp. (Box 39, Folder 147)
  - Comtés de Foix et Armagnac, et Rodez Supp. (Box 39, Folder 148)
  - (Hommages: Foix et Béarn1391 et 1398) (Box 39, Folder 149)
  - Foix, Armagnac, Rodez, 1392-1400 (Box 40, Folder 150)
  - Foix, Armagnac, Rodez Supp. (Box 40, Folder 151)
  - Foix, Armagnac, Rodez (homages), 1401 (Box 40, Folder 152)
  - Foix, Armagnac, Rodez, 1401-1418 (Box 41, Folder 153)
  - Foix, Armagnac, Rodez Supp. (Box 41, Folder 154)
  - Foix, Armagnac, Rodez, 1418-1429 (Box 41, Folder 155)
  - Foix, Armagnac, Rodez, 1436-1515 (Box 42, Folder 156-158)
  - Foix, Armagnac, Rodez Supp. (Box 42, Folder 159)
  - Foix, Armagnac, Rodez, 1516-1543 (Box 42, Folder 160)
  - Foix, Armagnac, Rodez (Box 43, Folder 161)
  - Foix, Armagnac, Rodez (236 hommages, +c), 1541 1544-1612 (Box 43, Folder 162)
  - Maisons de Périgond, Limoges, Lomagnes, et Auvillar, 1226-1574. (Box 43, Folder 163)
  - Vicomté de Lautres, 1557, comté de Dreux, 1180-1515. (Box 43, Folder 164)
  - Inventaire de diverses jurisdictions (Box 43, Folder 165)
  - Inventaire de diverses jurisdictions (Box 44, Folder 166)
  - Inventaire de diverses jurisdictions (Box 44, Folder 167)
  - Inventaires des archives du roi. Carcassonne. (Box 44, Folder 168-169)
  - Inventaires des archives du roi. Carcassonne. (Box 45, Folder 170)
  - Inventaires des archives du roi. Carcassonne. (Box 45, Folder 170)
    wanting
  - Registre des délibérations politiques de la maison consulaires de Nimes., 1621-1628. (Box 45, Folder 170)
  - [appendix: dosiers Cabié
    - I. Volumes et actes… qu'll me reste à utiliser … pour epuiser les documents. (Box 45, Folder 171)
    - II. Listes des actes à copier dans chaque volume.] (Box 45, Folder 172)
- Collection du Languedoc (Bénédictins) (Bibliothèque nationale)
  [Made up chiefly of papers of the Bénédietins Dom.Vaissète (c.1684-1756) and Dom. De Vic (1670-1734), editors of the "Histoite générale de Languedoc", which appeared 1730-1745. The collection is described by Ph. Lauer in "Bibl.Nat.,Coll. Man. s. 1'hist. des prov. de Fr: inventaire", pp.xiii-xv, and 193-252; partially in the "Cabinet historique", II, 2e partie, and III, 2e partie; and, briefly, in the "Bibliothèque de 1'Ecole des chartes", XXXII, 1871, pp.255f.]
  - [Table.] (Le Cabinet historique, vol.2., 2e partie.) (Box 46, Folder 173)
  - Géographic du Languedoc; mémoires and extraits.) (Box 46, Folder 173)
  - Notes géographiques sur chaque lieu: lettres. A-E (Box 46, Folder 174)
  - Notes géographiques sur chaque lieu: lettres. F.M (Box 46, Folder 175)
  - Notes géographiques sur chaque lieu: lettres. N-Z) (Box 46, Folder 176)
  - Notes géographiques: miscell.) (Box 46, Folder 176)
  - Cours d'eau.) (Box 46, Folder 176)
  - Localités, nomenclature et statistiqus) (Box 46, Folder 177)
  - Paroisses et communautés) (Box 46, Folder 177)
  - ... Instructions sur l'ordre civil de Languedoc ... demandées à Messieurs les curés ..., avec réponses, pour servir à la description géogr. et hist. des paroisses des diocèses languedociens: dioc. d'Agde (Box 47, Folder 178)
  - Dioc. d'Alet. (Box 47, Folder 179)
  - Dioc. de Béziers. (Box 47, Folder 180)
  - Dioc. de Castres (Box 47, Folder 181)
  - Dioc. de Carcassonne (Box 48, Folder 182)
  - Dioc. de Lavaur (Box 48, Folder 183)
  - Supplément (Box 48, Folder 184)
  - 2e Supplément (Box 48, Folder 184a)
  - Dioc. du Puy.) (Box 48, Folder 184a)
  - Dioc. de Mirepoix (Box 48, Folder 185)
  - Dioc. de Montpellier) (Box 48, Folder 185)
  - Dioc. de Narbonne (Box 48, Folder 186)
  - Dioc. de Rieux (Box 48, Folder 187)
  - Dioc. de Rieux: Supp. (Box 49, Folder 188)
    missing 9/80
  - Castelnandary; dioc. de Toulouse (Box 49, Folder 189)
  - Liste des communautés, consuls, et impositions (Box 49, Folder 190)
  - Mélanges d'hist. éccl.: dioc. Toulouse, Pamiers, Reiux, Montauban, Mirepoix (Box 50, Folder 191)
  - Mélanges d'hist. éccl.: dioc. Toulouse, Pamiers, Reiux, Montauban, Mirepoix: églises de S.Papoul, Lavaur, etc. (Box 50, Folder 192)
  - Listes chron. de gourverneurs, sénéchaux, et châtelains.. de Languedoc., (1226-). (Box 50, Folder 193-194)
  - Listes chron. de gourverneurs, sénéchaux, et châtelains.. de Languedoc. (1226-). Supplément (Box 51, Folder 195)
  - Mémoires, extraits et copies de decuments (Preuves) ayant servir [sic] pour 1'Histoirs de Languedoc., 409-1229 (Box 51, Folder 196)
  - Mémoires, extraits et copies de decuments (Preuves) ayant servir [sic] pour 1'Histoirs de Languedoc., 1201-1250 (Box 51, Folder 197)
  - Mémoires, extraits et copies de decuments (Preuves) ayant servir [sic] pour 1'Histoirs de Languedoc., 1251-1300 (Box 51, Folder 198)
  - Mémoires, extraits et copies de decuments (Preuves) ayant servir [sic] pour 1'Histoirs de Languedoc., 1301-1439 (Box 52, Folder 199-201)
  - Mémoires, extraits et copies de decuments (Preuves) ayant servir [sic] pour 1'Histoirs de Languedoc., 1401-1462 (Box 53, Folder 202)
  - Mémoires, extraits et copies de decuments (Preuves) ayant servir [sic] pour 1'Histoirs de Languedoc., 1461-1589 (Box 53, Folder 203-204)
  - Mémoires, extraits et copies de decuments (Preuves) ayant servir [sic] pour 1'Histoirs de Languedoc., 1561-1589 (Box 53, Folder 205)
    want
  - Généalogie et histoire des familles (Box 54, Folder 206-208)
  - Généalogie et histoire des familles supp: Lascure (Box 55, Folder 209)
  - Généalogie et histoire des familles (Box 55, Folder 210)
  - Comptes rendus du domaine de Sénéchaussée (Box 55, Folder 211)
    - A., 1272-1354. (Box 55, Folder 211)
    - B., 1354-1375 (Box 55, Folder 212)
    - C., 1375-1412 (Box 56, Folder 213)
    - D., 1412-1445 (Box 56, Folder 214)
    - E., 1445-1585 (Box 56, Folder 215)
    - supp. A. B. C. (Box 57, Folder 216)
    - supp D. E. (Box 57, Folder 217)
    - [appendices: dossiers Cabié] (Box 57, Folder 218)
  - Chartes de 1'abbaye de la Salvetat, au diocèse de Castres, 1057-1560. [small] (Box 57, Folder 219)
  - Supp. chartes du prieuré de Ségur au dioc. d'Albi [incomplete] (Box 58, Folder 220)
  - Notes on copying and on contents; "analyses" of 75-96, 108 and 109, and 150; bibliographical notes on other materials. (Box 58, Folder 221)
- Fonds Latin (Bibliothèque nationale)
  [Descriptions in:- "Catalogue codicum manuscriptorum bibliothecae regiae", 1739-1744; "Cabinet historique", XVIII, 2e partie, 1882; "Bibliothèque de 1'Ecole des chartes", 1863-1871 and 1874 (Delisle); (Bo2.10)]
  [The fonds consists of 18613 parts, of which Cabié copied only the following]:-
  - Registre de Raimond VII (13e s.) (Box 58, Folder 222)
  - Cartulaire de Lézat: fol. 1-99, (1240-1247) (Box 59, Folder 223)
  - Cartulaire de Lézat: 99-200, (1247-1249) (Box 59, Folder 224)
  - Cartulaire de Lézat: 201-300, (1247-1728) (Box 60, Folder 225)
  - Cartulaire de Lézat: [supp.] fol. 1-300 (Box 60, Folder 226)
  - app., analyse par Cablé] (Box 61, Folder 227)
    [For the above, see Delisle, in "Bibl. de 1'Ec.d.Ch.".,1864]
  - Recueils de D.Estiennot, Antiquités Bénédictines de la Gascogne, tome 1, (1680) (Box 61, Folder 228)
  - Recueils de D.Estiennot, Antiquités Bénédictines de la Gascogne, tome 2 (Box 61, Folder 229)
  - Recueils de D.Estiennot, Antiquités Bénédictines de la Ant. Bén. du Languedoc, tome 1 (Box 61, Folder 230)
  - Recueils de D.Estiennot, Antiquités Bénédictines de la Ant. Bén. du Languedoc, tome 2 (Box 62, Folder 231)
  - Recueils de D.Estiennot, Antiquités Bénédictines de la Fragmenta historiae Aquitaniae, t.1-7 (675) (Box 62, Folder 232)
  - Recueils de D.Estiennot, Antiquités Bénédictines de la Fragmenta historiae Aquitaniae, 8 (Box 62, Folder 233)
  - Recueils de D.Estiennot, Antiquités Bénédictines de la Fragmenta historiae Aquitaniae, 9 (Box 62, Folder 234)
  - Recueils de D.Estiennot. Fragmenta historiae Aquitaniae, t.10 (Box 63, Folder 235)
  - Recueils de D.Estiennot. Fragmenta historiae Aquitaniae, t.11 (Box 63, Folder 236)
  - Recueils de D.Estiennot. Fragmenta historiae Aquitaniae, t.12-14 (Box 63, Folder 237)
    [For the above, see Delisle, in "Bibl.de 1'Ec.d.ch.",1867]
- Fonds Français (Bibliothèque nationale)
  [Only 1-5093 described in "Catalogues des manuscrits français" 1868-1881, 4 vols.]
  - Registre des dépêches de M. de St.-Sulpice ambassadeur en Espagne, 1562-1565. (Box 63, Folder 238)
  - Registre des dépêches de M. de St.-Sulpice ambassadeur en Espagne, 1562-1565. (Box 63, Folder 239)
  - Registre des dépêches de M. de St.-Sulpice ambassadeur en Espagne, 1562-1565. (Box 64, Folder 240)
  - Dépêches du due de Ventadour, Lieut. gén. en Languedoc, au duc de Montmorency, Connestable de France. [1596…] (Box 64, Folder 241)
  - Inventaire du Trésor des chartes, par Dupuy, Tomes 5 + 6 (Box 64, Folder 242)
  - Inventaire des Registres du Trésor des Chartes (Box 64, Folder 243)
  - Registres A. du Trésor des Chartes (Box 65, Folder 244)
  - Registres L (Box 65, Folder 244)
  - Registres 1-26 (Box 65, Folder 244)
  - Registres 30 (1259-1272) (Box 65, Folder 245)
  - Registres 30 (Box 65, Folder 246)
  - Registres 31, 34-37 (Box 65, Folder 247)
  - Registres 38, 40, (1299-1309) (Box 66, Folder 248)
  - Registres 41 (1308-1309) (Box 66, Folder 249)
  - Registres 40-42 (1307-1308) (Box 66, Folder 250)